{"tossups": [{"question": "This university's plan may have been based on that of a failed attempt to create another university at Henricus seventy years prior. The first Greek letter society, Phi Beta Kappa, originated at this university in 1776. The missionary James Blair founded this university, whose students were originally required to declare their belief in the Thirty-Nine Articles, as this university was an Anglican institution at the time. Founded in 1693, this university was advocated for by the House of Burgesses. For ten points, name this university in Williamsburg, Virginia named for two British monarchs.", "answer": "The College of <u>William and Mary</u> in Virginia (prompt on W&M)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man heaped up a funeral pyre of horse saddles on which to immolate himself if he was in danger of being captured at a 451 battle in Gaul. Defeated at that Battle of the Catalaunian Plains by a Roman-Visigoth alliance, he later returned to Italy to renew his marriage claim to Honoria, though he was stopped outside Rome after meeting Pope Leo I. After the death of his brother Bleda, he became king of his people, the Huns. For ten points, name this \"Scourge of God.\"", "answer": "<u>Attila</u> the Hun", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Jeremiah Clarke wrote a \"voluntary\" for this instrument often played at weddings. J.S. Bach's second <em>Brandenburg Concerto</em> contains a challenging solo for the \"piccolo\" type of this instrument. Usually pitched in B-flat, this instrument is used to play many fanfares, and has a mellower tone than a cornet. For ten points, name this brass instrument with three valves, commonly used in classical and jazz music.", "answer": "<u>Trumpet</u>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This holiday was moved forward by a week after Fred Lazarus, Jr., the founder of Macy's, convinced Franklin Delano Roosevelt that the move would lengthen a shopping season. As described in <em>Mourt's Relation</em>, at the first known observation of this holiday in the New World, Susanna White and Mary Brewster helped prepare a feast. In 1621, this holiday celebration lasted for three days and was attended by 90 Wampanoag and 53 Pilgrims. For ten points, what is this holiday, celebrated in the U.S. on the fourth Thursday of November?", "answer": "<u>Thanksgiving</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This ethnic group's Borjigin clan employed Al-aud-Din to construct counterweighted trebuchets during a conquest that unseated the child-emperor Zhao Bing. This group destroyed the Jin under the leadership of Ogedei, and established their own dynasty after defeating the Song. For ten points, name this Asian civilization that established China's Yuan dynasty under the leadership of Kublai, the grandson of Genghis Khan.", "answer": "<u>Mongol</u>s  Page <b>1</b> of <b>10</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A solid form of this good created in 1875 was sometimes named \"Gala Peter\" in honor of Daniel Peter, the first to successfully combine its ingredients. A plant to produce this good was built in a town once known as Derry Church in Pennsylvania. A version of this good including peanuts was developed in 1930 by Franklin Mars. The founder of a company that sells this good invested capital from his earlier Lancaster Caramel Company. That man's namesake company introduced \"Kisses\" in 1907. For ten points, name this good sold since 1894 by Hershey's.", "answer": "Milk <u>chocolate</u>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This entity publishes a report informally known as the Beige Book and was formed partly as a result of the chaos caused by the Panic of 1907. This institution made massive purchases of T-bills and mortgage-backed securities after the 2008 real estate crisis as part of its program of  quantitative easing. This institution's Open Market Committee controls monetary policy by targeting the federal funds rate. For ten points, name this central banking system of the United States whose 16th chair person is Jay Powell.", "answer": "<u>Federal Reserve</u> System (accept \u201cThe Fed\u201d)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Economics"}, {"question": "Braxton Bragg won the first major battle in this state against William Rosecrans at Chickamauga, but a strategic setback for the Confederates at Kennesaw Mountain left the path to this state's capital open. Namesake \"neckties\" were used frequently in this state as part of a certain general's \"scorched earth\" policy. For ten points, name this state where Sherman's March to the Sea left a path of devastation to Savannah from its capital, Atlanta.", "answer": "<u>Georgia</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man sold one of his companies to Gil Amelio, against whom he later headed a coup to retake control of another of his companies. To promote one of his products, a hammer thrower smashing a screen was featured in a commercial during Super Bowl XVIII (18). After being ousted from his first company by John Sculley, this man went on to found NeXT and The Graphics Group, later renamed Pixar. For ten points, name this late rival of Microsoft's Bill Gates, who with Steve Wozniak co-founded Apple.", "answer": "Steve <u>Jobs</u>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This king served as the first Lord President of the Council of the North, which was created under his brother's reign. The Earl of Warwick secretly betrothed this man to his daughter, Isabel Neville, in an attempt to move closer to the throne. This brother of Edward IV became the last king of England to die in battle in 1485, which helped end the Wars of the Roses. The House of Tudor took power from, for ten points, what last king of the House of York who was killed at Bosworth Field?", "answer": "<u>Richard III</u> (accept <u>Richard of Gloucester</u>)  Page <b>2</b> of <b>10</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Facilities operated by this institution invented the first crash test dummies and seat belts. Nobel Laureate alumni of this institution include Pearl S. Buck and Toni Morrison. This institution is named for an associate of Samuel Morse who developed a method to lay telegraph lines and founded Western Union. In terms of enrollment, this Ithaca university is the largest in the Ivy League. For ten points, Columbia and what other university form the two Ivies in the state of New York?", "answer": "<u>Cornell</u> University", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man was stabbed to death after he had used the nickname \"Priapus\" to mock Cassius Chaerea. After abandoning his invasion of Britain, this man allegedly ordered his troops to collect seashells on the shores of Gaul as \"spoils of the sea.\" While traveling as a child with his father Germanicus, this emperor, whose birth name was Gaius, gained the nickname \"little boot.\" For ten points, name this Roman emperor who succeeded Tiberius and allegedly made his horse a consul.", "answer": "<u>Caligula</u> (accept <u>Gaius</u> before it is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "A ship from this country disappeared after fighting the German cruiser <em>Kormoran</em> some 180 miles southwest of Carnarvon in World War Two. This country's forces fought the Japanese in Papua New Guinea, a country only 200 miles north of this nation's mainland, and this country was the target of the Japanese raid on Darwin. For ten points, name this Commonwealth nation which operated the aircraft carrier HMAS<em> Melbourne</em> and lost the heavy cruiser HMAS <em>Sydney</em>.", "answer": "Commonwealth of <u>Australia</u>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "An opera about this man written on the 400th anniversary of his most famous undertaking was composed by Alberto Franchetti and premiered in the Teatro de Felice in this man's birthplace.  A Paul Claudel play inspired the libretto of another opera about this man that was composed by Darius Milhaud. The second act of Philip Glass's <em>The Voyage</em> ends with the First Mate exclaiming that he sighted land. That act begins with this man leaving the court of his patron Queen Isabella I. For ten points, name this Italian explorer best remembered for his 1492 journey to the New World.", "answer": "Christopher <u>Columbus</u>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "Robert E. Wood led this company in the 1930s, during which time his support of the America First movement caused him to crack down on employee unionization. One founder of this company originally hired the other founder to help support his watchmaking business.  Montgomery Ward was an early competitor to this company that began as a mail order catalog company, a division it discontinued in 1993. For ten points, name this Chicago-based former retail giant that once inhabited the building today known as the Willis Tower.", "answer": "<u>Sears</u>, Roebuck, and Company", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "This group attempted to work with U.S. forces in constructing a tunnel under Berlin during Operation Gold. This organization was embarrassed when Lionel Crabb disappeared while reconnoitering Portsmouth Dockyard. During the Cold War, this organization was infiltrated when Guy Burgess allowed the Soviet spy Kim Philby to join its ranks. This organization handled the ULTRA code during World War Two under the leadership of Stewart Menzies. For ten points, name this British agency that focuses on foreign intelligence, in contrast to its counterpart in Section 5.", "answer": "<u>MI6</u> (accept <u>Secret Intelligence Service</u> or <u>SIS</u>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man's vast selection of scientific works ranged from <em>The Power of Movement in</em> <em>Plants</em> to <em>The Expression of the Emotions in Man and Animals</em>. His best known theory was defended in 1860 by Thomas Henry Huxley, who was known as this man's \"bulldog.\" This man wrote about his theory of sexual selection in <em>The Descent of Man</em>. This man studied finches in the Galapagos while voyaging on the HMS <em>Beagle</em>. For ten points, name this English naturalist who authored <em>On the</em> <em>Origin of the Species</em>.", "answer": "Charles <u>Darwin</u>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "Irvin McDowell led a failed offensive in this state against forces under P. G. T. Beauregard.  Stonewall Jackson was killed at one bloody Confederate victory in this state where Lee split his forces to encircle Hooker's. George B. McClellan's early cautious offensive against this state's capital initially proceeded well, until his Army of the Potomac was countered by Confederate forces under this state's native son, Robert E. Lee. For ten points, name this Southern state where repeated Union armies attempted to take the Confederate capital.", "answer": "Commonwealth of <u>Virginia</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>During this man's term, Surgeon General Leroy Burney became the first public official</u></b> <b><u>to identify the link between cigarettes and cancer. This man believed in reductions of</u></b> <b><u>conventional forces due to increased nuclear forces, and a member of this man's cabinet</u></b> <b><u>coined the term</u> (+) \"massive retaliation.\" That Secretary of State under this man helped plan coups in Guatemala and Iran with his brother Allen. John Foster</b>(*) Dulles was Secretary of State under this man whose vice president was Richard Nixon. For ten points, name this U.S. president for most of the 1950s.", "answer": "Dwight D(avid) \u201cIke\u201d <u>Eisenhower</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man's visit to the farm of Iowa resident Roswell Garst helped provide inspiration</u></b> <b><u>for his Virgin Lands agricultural campaign. After this man's policies were attacked by</u></b> <b><u>Lorenzo Sumulong in front of the UN, this man</u> (+) took off his shoe and began banging a table. This man had earlier shocked his own nation by delivering the \"Secret Speech\" in which he denounced the </b>(*) \"cult of personality\" that surrounded his predecessor. For ten points, name this Soviet leader who succeeded Joseph Stalin.", "answer": "Nikita <u>Khruschev</u>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man never premiered his works in Paris again after the Jockey Club used a</u></b> <b><u>performance of his</u> </b><em><b><u>Tannhauser</u></b></em><b><u> [TAHN-hoyz-er] to stage a demonstration against Napoleon</u></b> <b><u>III. This man's music was criticized as pandering to extremists in the</u> </b><em><b><u>Untimely Meditations</u></b></em><b><u> of</u></b> <b><u>Friedrich</u> (+) Nietzsche, which includes an essay about this man in Bayreuth [BYE-roit]. This man's debt was settled by Ludwig II of Bavaria, under whose patronage he </b> <b>premiered </b>(*) Tristan und Isolde. For ten points, name this notedly anti-Semitic composer of the <em>Ring</em> Cycle.", "answer": "Richard <u>Wagner</u>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Opera"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man declared a year in which no crops could be grown and killed citizens who</u></b> <b><u>did not mourn enough after the death of this man's mother, Nandi. This man's conquests led</u></b> <b><u>to a period of widespread warfare known as \"the crushing.\" This man defeated</u> (+) Zwide, killer of the Mthethwa chief Dingiswayo, in a civil war and was in turn assassinated by his half-brothers, Dingane and Mhlangana. This man replaced the assegai with the iklwa, which his </b>(*) impi troops utilized in the \"buffalo horns\" formation. For ten points, name this great Zulu king.", "answer": "<u>Shaka</u> Zulu (accept <u>Shaka</u> kaSenzangakhona)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A laboratory with this name had scientists who demonstrated the wave nature of</u></b> <b><u>matter and created the transistor. A company founded by a man with this surname agreed to</u></b> <b><u>the Kingsbury Commitment with the government and later split into</u> (+) \"baby\" versions, like Verizon. A man with this surname called his assistant Thomas Watson to come to his room by using a device he invented. That Scottish man with this surname founded American </b>(*) Telephone and Telegraph. For ten points, the first practical telephone was invented by a man with what surname?", "answer": "<u>Bell</u> (accept Alexander Graham <u>Bell</u>)  Page <b>9</b> of <b>10</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>After one battle for this city, the losing commander was strangled by a silk cord upon</u></b> <b><u>returning home thanks to his failure to breach the defenses of Ernst von Starhemberg. The</u></b> <b><u>croissant was allegedly invented during a battle for this city that was saved from</u> (+) Kara Mustafa by the arrival of Jan III Sobieski in 1683. Suleiman the Magnificent's 1529 attempt to capture this city marked the peak of Ottoman expansion in </b>(*) Europe. For ten points, name this capital of the Holy Roman Empire and modern day Austria.", "answer": "<u>Vienna</u>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This artist's</u> </b><em><b><u>The Lictors Bring to Brutus the Bodies of His Sons</u></b></em><b><u> was painted to</u></b> <b><u>symbolize the ideas of sacrificing for the greater good and equality before the law. This</u></b> <b><u>artist's depiction of a story from Plato's</u> (+) </b><em><b>Phaedo</b></em><b> is on loan to MOMA, and he depicted an emperor he admired greatly in </b><em><b>Napoleon </b>(*) Crossing the Alps</em>. For ten points, name this influential French Neoclassical painter, known for <em>The Death of Socrates</em> and <em>The Death of Marat</em>.", "answer": "Jacques-Louis <u>David</u>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>After Howard Metzenbaum accused this man of never having had a job, this man</u></b> <b><u>secured his party's primary nomination by giving the Gold Star Mothers speech. John McCain</u></b> <b><u>and this man were reelected</u> (+) despite being found to have exercised poor judgement by accepting campaign contributions from Charles Keating. A radio glitch prevented this man from hearing Scott Carpenter's Godspeed message to </b>(*) Friendship 7. For ten points, name this first American to orbit the Earth.", "answer": "John <u>Glenn</u>  <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker!", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Victor Hugo's</u> </b><em><b><u>Les Mis\u00e9rables</u></b></em><b><u> claimed that the fate of Europe would have been</u></b> <b><u>changed had it not rained the night before this battle. At the beginning of \"Grass,\" the</u></b> <b><u>speaker tells the reader to \"pile the bodies high at</u> (+) Austerlitz and\" this battle. Fabrizio del Dongo fights at this battle under Marshal Ney in </b><em><b>The Charterhouse of Parma</b></em><b>. George Osborne is killed in this battle while fighting under the </b>(*) Duke of Wellington in <em>Vanity Fair</em>. For ten points, name this final defeat of Napoleon.", "answer": "Battle of <u>Waterloo</u>", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Long Fiction"}, {}], "bonuses": []}